<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Block / the data on Models for missing data</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/</link><description>Recent content in Block / the data on Models for missing data</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Response info</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/response-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/response-info/</guid><description>Response information # The usual case # In the usual case, we are working with a single vector of observations (a single column of data in a flat file). Below, we see the first few lines of the data block for an analysis of count-type data from Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument (LIBI), in Montana (a park within the Rocky Mountain Network). The file, rich.yml, lives in the directory assets/uplands-config/ROMN/LIBI.</description></item><item><title>Location info</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/site-loc-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/site-loc-info/</guid><description>Location info # Site location information (site location info), if provided, is used to evaluate spatial autocorrelation in model residuals.
site location info: file: assets/uplands-data/ROMN/LIBI_GRKO_metrics_adjwt_20170414_forCSP.csv coordinate columns: - xcoord - ycoord Here again, we point to the name of the file (file) and supply the names of the columns containing the spatial coordinates (coordinate columns). Note that proper residual analysis requires Cartesian coordinates. If the locations come directly from a geographic coordinate system, they&amp;rsquo;ll need to be transformed to a projected coordinate system.</description></item><item><title>Covariate info</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/covariate-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/config-files/block-data/covariate-info/</guid><description>Covariate info # Covariate information (covariate info), if provided, is joined to the response information prior to model fitting. It&amp;rsquo;s used only in models for which predictors are specified.
covariate info: file: assets/uplands-data/ROMN/LIBI_Covariates_AllSitesAllYears_20201104_Through2016_with_exotics.csv event date info: date-time column: Year date-time format: Y! As with the other statements in the data block, we point to the name of the covariate file (file; see the covariate data section for more detail) and, if different from the date attributes in the response data, supply info required to properly parse covariate datetime fields.</description></item></channel></rss>