<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Welcome on Models for missing data</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/</link><description>Recent content in Welcome on Models for missing data</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Conditions</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/conditions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/conditions/</guid><description>Conditions # Modify the default behavior of pred-type means.
Syntax # trend conditions: Botanist: JA Usage # See the object types entry for a more thorough introduction to this topic.</description></item><item><title>Installation</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/0-getting-started/installation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/0-getting-started/installation/</guid><description>Installation # Obtaining a copy of the repository # New here? # To clone the repository, open a terminal1 and run the following command from the directory into which you&amp;rsquo;d like to place the project (e.g., from ~/repos).
git clone https://github.com/lzachmann/models-for-missing-data.git [DIRNAME] DIRNAME is optional, and specifies the name of the directory into which the project will be cloned on your local machine. You could call it &amp;ldquo;m4md&amp;rdquo; for instance, if you wanted something a bit</description></item><item><title>Likelihood function</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/likelihood-function/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/likelihood-function/</guid><description>Likelihood function # The likelihood statement specifies the probability distribution that will be used to describe the response variable. The available options depend on your data, so knowing what type of variable you&amp;rsquo;re working with is essential.
Syntax # # Likelihood. For counts, one or both of: poisson, negative-binomial. likelihood: - poisson - negative-binomial Usage # In some cases &amp;ndash; a model for soil stability observations &amp;ndash; there is only one plausible, implemented likelihood function (ordinal-latent-normal).</description></item><item><title>Model builder</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/4-internals/model-builder/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/4-internals/model-builder/</guid><description>Model builder # The shell script compile-jags-file.sh builds JAGS model files using several arguments. The arguments &amp;ndash; which correspond to the likelihood, the deterministic function, group-level effects parameterization (random intercepts and slopes vs. random intercepts only), the presence or absence of additional covariates and, finally, the path to write to &amp;ndash; are supplied via the &amp;lsquo;MODEL&amp;rsquo; block in the YAML file for an analysis. For purposes of development or debugging, compile-jags-file.</description></item><item><title>Non-ignorable missingness</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/non-ignorable-missingness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/non-ignorable-missingness/</guid><description>Statistics is basically a missing data problem!
&amp;ndash; Little 2013
Nearly all samples &amp;ndash; whether by design or by accident &amp;ndash; are incomplete. We very rarely make a complete census of all individuals in a population or all sites on a landscape. Sometimes we don&amp;rsquo;t collect, or can&amp;rsquo;t collect, complete information for individual samples or measures. For instance, we might know an animal was alive when it was last seen, so we know it survived at least that long, but know nothing about its current status.</description></item><item><title>Response data</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/a-data/i-y-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/a-data/i-y-info/</guid><description>Response data # The response data include the observations we are trying to model, as well as columns with identifiers (indices, IDs, datetime strings) for all relevant sampling design information. Elements of the sampling design often seen in long-term monitoring data include the following:
Design element Examples observational units transect, quadrat, plot sampling units plot, site stratification stratum date / event times MM/DD/YYYY, YYYY Format # The response data are stored as flat files.</description></item><item><title>Response info</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-data/response-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-data/response-info/</guid><description>Response information # The usual case # In the usual case, we are working with a single vector of observations (a single column of data in a flat file). Below, we see the first few lines of the data block for an analysis of count-type data from Little Bighorn Battlefield National Monument (LIBI), in Montana (a park within the Rocky Mountain Network). The file, rich.yml, lives in the directory assets/uplands-config/ROMN/LIBI.</description></item><item><title>Covariate data</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/a-data/ii-x-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/a-data/ii-x-info/</guid><description>Covariate data # Covariates are variables that are expected to change with the response variable &amp;ndash; they covary in some way with the observations we seek to model. The definition of covariates varies widely online and in the literature. For our purposes, we use the term covariate to describe any variable (whether continuous or discrete) that might influence the mean of the response variable we are interested in. In many cases their effects are of direct interest in the analysis (weather or terrain, for instance).</description></item><item><title>Disentangling concepts of status, trend, and trajectory</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/trend-vs-trajectory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/trend-vs-trajectory/</guid><description>The terms status and trend are ubiquitous in resource monitoring and management settings. To be useful and robust, however, they require precise (mathematical) definitions. It has been my experience that misunderstanding these terms can lead to misapplication of model predictions and to researchers and managers drawing the wrong conclusions from the data. In this post we show how relatively simple, even intuitive, definitions for each of these terms clarifies their intent, and improves the insights provided by models of monitoring data.</description></item><item><title>Finite population correction</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/finite-pop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/finite-pop/</guid><description>Finite population correction # When the size of the sample collected is a significant proportion of the overall population, then we must use a finite population correction, a topic we introduce briefly in another post.
Syntax # finite population correction: true finite population info: file: assets/uplands-data/ROMN/LIBI_SampledUnsampled_Ratio.csv columns with the number of sampled and unsampled sites: - &amp;#39;# sampled sites&amp;#39; - &amp;#39;# unsampled sites&amp;#39; covariate info includes unsampled sites: true Usage #</description></item><item><title>Link function</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/link-function/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/link-function/</guid><description>Link function # The deterministic link function for the regression on the mean ensures that the mean we are trying to model has the appropriate support for the probability distribution from which our observations arise.
deterministic model: - linear - exponential</description></item><item><title>Location info</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-data/site-loc-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-data/site-loc-info/</guid><description>Location info # Site location information (site location info), if provided, is used to evaluate spatial autocorrelation in model residuals.
site location info: file: assets/uplands-data/ROMN/LIBI_GRKO_metrics_adjwt_20170414_forCSP.csv coordinate columns: - xcoord - ycoord Here again, we point to the name of the file (file) and supply the names of the columns containing the spatial coordinates (coordinate columns). Note that proper residual analysis requires Cartesian coordinates. If the locations come directly from a geographic coordinate system, they&amp;rsquo;ll need to be transformed to a projected coordinate system.</description></item><item><title>Requirements</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/0-getting-started/requirements/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/0-getting-started/requirements/</guid><description>Requirements # The requirements include R (v4.X.X) and RStudio (if you&amp;rsquo;d like to work with models-for-missing-data interactively), and JAGS (v4.3.0). Git and Git Bash (for Windows users) are convenient if you&amp;rsquo;d like to stay up to date with the latest changes.
The requirements (including a few non-essentials) are described in the latest Dockerfile. You&amp;rsquo;re likely to need everything you see beneath install2.r in the instructions below. You can install these from your R console with install.</description></item><item><title>Covariate info</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-data/covariate-info/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-data/covariate-info/</guid><description>Covariate info # Covariate information (covariate info), if provided, is joined to the response information prior to model fitting. It&amp;rsquo;s used only in models for which predictors are specified.
covariate info: file: assets/uplands-data/ROMN/LIBI_Covariates_AllSitesAllYears_20201104_Through2016_with_exotics.csv event date info: date-time column: Year date-time format: Y! As with the other statements in the data block, we point to the name of the covariate file (file; see the covariate data section for more detail) and, if different from the date attributes in the response data, supply info required to properly parse covariate datetime fields.</description></item><item><title>Group-level effects</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/group-level-effects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/group-level-effects/</guid><description>Group-level effects # The basic motivation for random group-level effects is that sites matter. They are an essential feature of the sampling design. Having no such random effects would imply that sites don&amp;rsquo;t matter and observations can be pooled (as if they were collected from a completely random sample).1
Group-level effects incorporate differences among sites (that may be impossible to model with covariates) to inform park-level trends. They allow each site to have its intercept (and potentially, its slope) drawn from a common / underlying distribution of intercepts (and slopes).</description></item><item><title>Marginal effects</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/marginal-effects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/marginal-effects/</guid><description>Marginal effects # Summaries of the association between a change in a regressor and a change in the response variable.
Syntax # drivers: true Usage # When drivers: true, the model API creates additional JAGS objects, which are used to evaluate the marginal effects of explanatory variables in the model. By default, it shows the effect of each variable holding all other variables at zero (the mean of scaled continuous variables and the reference level of categorical variables).</description></item><item><title>Quickstart</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/0-getting-started/quickstart/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/0-getting-started/quickstart/</guid><description>Quickstart # Assuming you&amp;rsquo;ve got the models-for-missing-data project code (see Installation) and have all of the dependencies (see Requirements), the last remaining pieces you&amp;rsquo;ll need to begin running models are the data and analysis config files. We&amp;rsquo;ve included examples of each in the &amp;ldquo;assets/&amp;rdquo; directory. See the guide for more information about each of these components of the models-for-missing-data workflow. You can find an example of the data here, and an analysis config file for these data here.</description></item><item><title>Unequal inclusion probabilities</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/unequal-inclusion-probability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/unequal-inclusion-probability/</guid><description>The Sonoran Desert is among the most extreme environments on Earth. Sampling in these remote, rugged landscapes requires a different approach. When the Park Service established monitoring in Organ Pipe Cactus National Monument they used an approach to select sites based on the cost of travel to sites on the broader landscape, visiting less &amp;ldquo;costly&amp;rdquo; sites with higher probability than more costly sites. The cost surface that defined the probability of inclusion of sites was developed using terrain data, and a tool that estimates the time to travel to any arbitrary location on the landscape.</description></item><item><title>Posterior predictive checks</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/ppc-facets/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/ppc-facets/</guid><description>Posterior predictive checks # By default, the posterior predictive checks produced by the model API include stratum_id and unit_code. We include these elements by default because they correspond directly to subscripts in the model. You can specify additional variables for post-hoc model checking via ppc facets. Performing posterios predictive checks is an essential step in modeling process. These checks essentially allow you to evaluate whether your model can generate new data that are similar to your observed data.</description></item><item><title>Sampling and populations</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/sampling-and-populations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/sampling-and-populations/</guid><description>We sample for a very practical reason. It&amp;rsquo;s usually impossible to get information on the whole population, so we use a sample to make inferences about the population. In our case, the population is typically all sites in a stratum or all sites &amp;ndash; in all strata &amp;ndash; at the scale of an entire park. Typically, the inference we seek entails three questions.
What&amp;rsquo;s the best estimate of the population mean?</description></item><item><title>Variances</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/variances/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/variances/</guid><description>Variances # As with group-level effects for the intercept or time slope terms, each site can also have its own variance.
Syntax # variances: stratum-level fixed: level: stratum type: fixed response column(s): - native.rich - native.forb.rich site-level hierarchical: level: site type: hier response column(s): - native.rich - native.forb.rich Usage # The entries beneath response column(s) have to be column names, not variable descriptions.</description></item><item><title>Covariates</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/covariates/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/covariates/</guid><description>Covariates # The predictors to use for modeling the mean of the response variable.
Syntax # additional covariates: - Botanist (JA) - Botanist (JA), deficit.pregr Usage # For categorical variables (e.g., Botanist), the optional parenthetical declaration can do one of two things.
It sets the reference level for dummy-coded variables. In the case of Botanist (JA), the reference level becomes the botanist with initials JA.</description></item><item><title>Exposure / offset</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/exposure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-extras/exposure/</guid><description>Exposure / offset #</description></item><item><title>Initial values</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/inits/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/docs/1-guide/b-config-files/block-model/inits/</guid><description>Initial values # Initial values determine the starting point of the sampler, and can play a large role in ensuring efficient sampling and convergence. Implementing some degree of randomness is also important when defining initial values to ensure that a model is able to converge properly for a range of initial values. Providing initial values that are within or near the posterior distribution of the parameter of interest serves not only to speed up convergence, but also to optimize the efficiency of the sampler (i.</description></item><item><title>Interpreting coefficients</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/interpreting-coefficients/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/interpreting-coefficients/</guid><description>Making sense of the effects of variables included as predictors # Some aspects of covariate effects are readily apparent &amp;ndash; for instance, the sign of a coefficient in a model says at least something about the general directionality of the effect, positive or negative. However, a deeper understanding of a model typically requires inferences that go well beyond simple measures of the directionality or significance of effects &amp;ndash; it requires understanding the size of effects.</description></item><item><title>Stratum-varying fixed effects</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/stratum-varying-fixed-effects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/stratum-varying-fixed-effects/</guid><description>Assume we have three strata, \(s_0\) , \(s_1\) , and \(s_2\) , where \(s_0\) is the &amp;ldquo;reference&amp;rdquo; stratum – in other words, \(s_0\) is the stratum for which the 0/1 indicator is 0 across the board in the indicator matrix below (the first row):
\[\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 0 \\ 1 &amp;amp; 1 &amp;amp; 0 \\ 1 &amp;amp; 0 &amp;amp; 1 \end{bmatrix}\] B_0 + (B_1 + B_1_s1_offset * s1 + B_1_s2_offset * s2) * x_1 # in stratum s0 B_0 + (B_1) * x_1 # in stratum s1 B_0 + (B_1 + B_1_s1_offset * s1) * x_1 # in stratum s2 B_0 + (B_1 + B_1_s2_offset * s2) * x_1 # lm(y~x1*x2) model.</description></item><item><title>The offset term</title><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/offsets/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/posts/offsets/</guid><description>Counts of things naturally scale with the length or duration of observation, the area sampled, and sampling intensity (Citation: McElreath,&amp;#32;2018McElreath,&amp;#32; R.&amp;#32; (2018). &amp;#32;Statistical rethinking: A bayesian course with examples in r and stan. &amp;#32; Chapman; Hall/CRC. ) . For instance, the longer the river stretch we survey, the more fish we&amp;rsquo;ll tend to find.
Offset terms are used to model rates &amp;ndash; e.g., counts per unit area or time. In the context of the model, the offset term transforms the response variable from a rate to a count.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/menu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://lzachmann.github.io/models-for-missing-data/menu/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>